טוב, Tove,
today's דף daf is מ"ו, Mem-vav, we pick up two lines from
the top and we are going through the things in the משנה
Mishnah that although their פיגול pigul is a limited category, it doesn't
apply to the מתיר matir of a קרבן, korban, the דם, dam,
the קומץ, kometz, לבונה, levonah, etc. The other things that sometimes get
discussed with פיגול, pigul, טומאה tumah and נותר notar and טמא. tamei.
נותר notar is the stuff is left over night and then it's
an איסור כרת issur kares to eat it. טמא tamei is if
you're טמא, tamei, it's אסור assur to eat those things. Again, איסור
כרת. issur kares. The reason those three come together is that there's
an איסור כרת, issur kares, the prohibition of כרת, kares, of divine
excision, if somebody were to do that, were to eat it, not
to actually create it, but to eat it. So those other two
categories of נותר notar and טמא tamei have a broader application. They
do apply to the מתיר matir and that we learned out yesterday
because the פסוקים pesukim are read sort of be more broader. אשר
יקדישו בני ישראל asher yaktishu b'nei Yisrael or אשר הם מקדישים לי
asher heim maktishim li to be more inclusive, to include these things
that are the מתיר: matir: דם, dam, קומץ, kometz, לבונה, levonah, etc.
But blood even though it's the מתיר matir is not included. There's
not an obligation on blood if it is left over and one
eats it. I mean there's a כרת kares for eating blood, but
there's not an additional כרת kares for נותר notar and there's not
an additional כרת kares for טומאה. tumah. Okay, so why not? Let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
You can get multiple כרת? kares?
Well, I guess the נפקא מינה nafka mina would be for example
if you did it בשוגג beshogeg to bring multiple קרבנות חטאת korbanot
chatat or what's not sort of, or if you got warned against
it to get lashes, multiple lashes. And also what's not mentioned in
the גמרא Gemara but is, I was wondering about is that there's
a principle that for the איסור issur of דם, dam, if you
cooked the blood, it's not raw, you don't transgress the איסור issur
of דם. dam. But I believe or not the דאורייתא, d'oraisa, not
the כרת kares of דם dam at least. I wonder, I don't
know what the הלכה halacha is, I haven't checked what the הלכה
halacha is in terms of this issue of נותר notar and טמא,
tamei, but that might, you know, at least in theory. Anyway, but
the point is is that even though in theory there would be
relevance to saying that you get two prohibitions, you do not. דם
dam is excluded from נותר notar and טמא tamei and the question
is why? So מנא הני מילי? Minany Milei? Where is this from?
אמר עולא אמר קרא, Amar Ulla amar kra, the verse says,
ואני נתתיו לכם על המזבח לכפר. V'ani nasati lachem al hamizbeach l'chaper.
Okay, this is when God says don't eat blood because I've given
it for you on the altar to atone. So the דרשה drasha
says, I've given it to you, לכם, lachem, שלכם יהא. shelachem yehei.
It's yours. It's not really fully the Divine's and God's and so
on, so therefore and there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Now, the דרשות drashos
here, they're going to be three דרשות drashos that and רש"י Rashi
says this original, this original little set of דרשות drashos is not,
was not originally said in this context. It was originally said in
a different context to say how do we know there's no מעילה
me'ilah by the blood? And what the גמרא Gemara is still going
to do is going to be that there's gonna be three verses
that there's no מעילה me'ilah by the blood and therefore say, ah,
why do you need all three? Well, they're really telling you three
things: there's no מעילה, me'ilah, there's no איסור issur of נותר, notar,
and there's no איסור issur of טמא. tamei. Now this is quite
fascinating, right? I mean, one wonders if there's some deeper theological point
that is being made here, that the very blood which is the
מתיר matir and is the thing on which the entire קרבן korban
rests, and for the גמרא's Gemara insistence that it's not about the
burning of the אימורים, emurim, which by the way we should just
mention for a second is fascinating, right? Because if you think about
all of the narratives in the תורה Torah where somebody offers a
קרבן, korban, it's the putting it on the fire and the smoke
rising to heaven, and the תורה Torah even in ויקרא Vayikra constantly
uses the phrase ריח ניחוח, rei'ach nicho'ach, a pleasing odor. And rabbis
say, no, no, no, that's not at all what the קרבן korban
is about. The קרבן korban is just about the blood, presumably based
on this verse, ואני נתתיו לכם על המזבח לכפר. V'ani nasati lachem
al hamizbeach l'chaper. So this verse really says nothing matters to make
the קרבן korban good, the only thing that matters is the blood.
In somehow exactly that blood is excluded from פיגול, pigul, excluded from
נותר notar and טמא. tamei. So it's one thing to say maybe
those things, those are who knows, invalidities and maybe somehow they don't
apply,
but the idea that there's no מעילה. me'ilah. That this is the
very thing which is given to be on the altar, to given
to God as it were, and therefore to achieve atonement. The point
is, oh, but it's yours, it's not God's because it's therefore atoning
and therefore there's no מעילה. me'ilah. Like there's something very bizarre about
that, right? That there's, it's part of the sanctified part of the
animal. The one part of the animal that there's no מעילה me'ilah
on is the part that דווקא davka is put on the altar,
and going to God. So I don't know, maybe it has to
do with the fact that somehow it represents the life force. And
by representing the life force and not just something physical, you know
what I mean? So then therefore somehow that's part of why it's
excluded. But anyway, so let's read this. It's a, I think it's
certainly worth just thinking for a moment about how ironic this is.
ואני נתתיו לכם, V'ani nasati lachem, שלכם יהא. shelachem yehei.
So it's yours, there's no מעילה. me'ilah. דבי רבי ישמעאל תנא אמר
קרא Dvei Rebbi Yishmael tana amar kra לכפר, l'chaper, I have given
it to you that's next word to atone on the altar. לכפרה
נתתיו ולא למעילה, L'chaparah nasativ v'lo l'meilah, it's there to achieve atonement
but not that you should be somehow like נכשל nichshal by it,
not that you should transgress if you benefited by it. Okay. רבי
יוחנן אמר אמר קרא Rebbi Yochanan amar amar kra the verse says
הוא, hu, כי הדם הוא בנפש יכפר, ki hadam hu banefesh yechaper,
the blood is that through which you achieve atonement. הוא לפני כפרה
כלאחר כפרה hu lifnei chaparah kele'achar chaparah it has the same status
before achieved atonement and after it achieved atonement. So מה לאחר כפרה
אין בו מעילה ma le'achar chaparah ein bo meila since it’s obvious
that after it’s put on the altar there's no מעילה, meila, we'll
say why that's obvious in a minute. So therefore, and we’re saying
that it always has the same status, אף לפני כפרה אין בו
מעילה, af lifnei chaparah ein bo meila, the same is true before
כפרה. chaparah. So now the גמרא Gemara says one minute, אימא לאחר
כפרה כליפני כפרה, eima le'achar chaparah kelifnei chaparah, fine, before and after
are the same. But why do you start by the like the
rock solid assumption that after it’s on the altar there's no מעילה
meila and then apply it to before it goes on the altar?
Say the reverse. Since normally things that are part of a קרבן
korban have מעילה, meila, that’s true before it was on the altar.
If this is equating them, then even after it’s on the altar
there’s still going to be
מעילה. meila. אימא לאחר כפרה כליפני כפרה מה לפני כפרה יש בו
מעילה אף לאחר כפרה יש בו מעילה. eima le'achar chaparah kelifnei chaparah
ma lifnei chaparah yesh bo meila af le'achar chaparah yesh bo meila.
Okay, so why, why is it so obvious to you that it’s
impossible there’s מעילה meila after it’s on the altar? So the
גמרא Gemara answers אין לך דבר שנעשית מצותו ומועלים בו ein lecha
davar shena'aseit mitzvato umo'alin bo because we have a principle which is,
there is nothing once the מצוה mitzvah is done with, with, to
it, that there’s still מעילה. meila. מעילה meila sort of is because
like it’s designated for a holy purpose, okay, and once it’s somehow
has served that purpose, it’s נעשית מצותו, na'aseit mitzvato, then its status
is like, you know, it’s sort of like it’s depleted or it’s
like, you know, it’s, it’s fulfilled its designation and therefore it goes
into a different הלכתית halachic state. Okay, so especially if you think
about מעילה meila again there’s like could be two types of מעילה,
meila, right? There’s מעילה meila by בדק הבית bedek habayit which is
just temple, the בית המקדש beit hamikdash owns something. So there מעילה
meila could be more of a type of like of a גזל,
gezel, of appropriating something that isn’t yours. Here where something that is
sanctified for the altar, מעילה meila could be more of a problem
of like of, you know, of like of, turning it off course,
of, of, you
know,
not so much of appropriation but as much as like of, of,
of misuse, and of, and of, you know, diverting its course. So
therefore once it’s achieved its goal, and this is specifically about קדשי
מזבח, kodshei mizbeach, right? There is no מצותו mitzvato by things that
are owned by בדק הבית bedek habayit that’s just property. But then
there’s no more מעילה. meila. Okay, by the way, a similar הלכה
halacha is if that there was something that’s אסור בהנאה asur behana'ah
that there’s a מצוה mitzvah to burn, okay, like חמץ chametz while
it depends if we פסקן pasken this way but חמץ chametz there’s
a מצוה mitzvah to burn it. But anyway, then once you burn
it, it’s no longer אסור בהנאה. asur behana'ah. Why? Because the principle
is basically the same, נעשית מצותו. na'aseit mitzvato. The תורה Torah wanted
you to get it to a certain state, now to turn it
into charcoal, now you got it to that state, so now it’s
basically telling you you’re done with it. So now it’s, you know,
so, so, and now it reaches a different הלכתית halachic status. So
here too anyway, something that is נעשית מצותו na'aseit mitzvato that belongs
on the מזבח mizbeach there’s no longer מעילה. meila. So since by
blood that will certainly be after you put it on the altar,
so therefore that’s true even before you put it on the altar
because of this פסוק pasuk of הוא. hu. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this,
ולא, velo, is that really true that you don’t have anything once
the מצוה mitzvah is done that there’s no מעילה? meila? והרי תרומת
הדשן. ve-harei trumat hadeshen. There’s תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen that the פסוק
pasuk says you take the, the ashes off of the outer altar
and you put them down by the side of the ramp, and,
and, I don’t know, oh here’s the picture, okay, so you take
the ashes off of the altar in the morning and you put
a little bit of here down by the east side of the
ramp, okay, and that’s the מצוה mitzvah to do with the ashes.
And so that’s נעשית מצותו, na'aseit mitzvato, once these ashes are put
here the מצוה mitzvah was done with them. But the דרשה drasha
is going to be והניחם שם, vehineicham sham, they have to remain
there and cannot be used for anything else and they have to,
now of course if you leave them there there’s gonna be a
big pile of ashes after a while but the point is that
חז"ל chazal understood that it sort of got absorbed, you know, in
its place. But the point here is that once it’s put there
it remains forbidden in use, okay, even after the מצוה mitzvah was
done, the מצוה mitzvah of putting it by there. So look, there’s
something that is נעשית מצותו na'aseit mitzvato that’s still forbidden. So it
says ולא והרי תרומת הדשן? velo veharei trumat hadeshen? משום דהוה תרומת
הדשן ובגדי כהונה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד, mishum dehava trumat hadeshen ubigdei
kehuna shnei ktuvim habaim ke'echad,
no,
because there are two exceptions. And if there are two exceptions then
it means you can’t say that that’s the rule, it means that
those are the exceptions because if the, if it were the rule
you wouldn’t have to make say, you know, repeat
the, say, you know, here’s the rule by תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen
and here, you know, here’s the הלכה halacha over here. If תרומת
הדשן trumat hadeshen were the general principle then just say it once.
The fact that it’s saying תרומת הדשן trumat hadeshen and the clothes
of the כהנים, kohanim, we’ll see the כהן גדול kohen gadol after
יום כיפור Yom Kippur are still forbidden. So the fact that you
have to point it out in two places means that they’re the
exception to the rule, not the rule. What’s the case of בגדי
כהונה? bigdei kehuna? וכל שני כתובים הבאים כאחד אין מלמדין. vechol shnei
ktuvim habaim ke'echad ein melamdin.
Okay, so we’ll see that’s the בגדים bgadim of the, of the,
what do you call it, of the כהן גדול kohen gadol because
it says after he’s done with them on יום כיפור והניחם שם,
Yom Kippur vehineicham sham, he shall leave them there. Okay, so as
I, by the ashes it says ושמו, vesamo, I think I might
have quoted the פסוק pasuk by the כהן גדול kohen gadol a
minute ago, but anyway, so here by the ashes it says ושמו
אצל המזבח vesamo etzel hamizbeach and we’re gonna learn that that’s what
has to remain, you can't use it for anything else, and by
the בגדי כהונה bigdei kehuna it says והניחם שם, vehinnicham sham, so
leave them there. Now, by the way, just because it says that
you have to leave them there doesn't prove that מעילה me'ila still
applies. Somehow the גמרא'ס Gemara's assuming that since they have to be
left and not disturbed or whatever, not reused, that indicates that their
status, you know, that the מעילה me'ila status continues. So the גמרא
Gemara says, okay, but those are the two cases, and therefore we're
going to assume unless we're forced to say otherwise, we're going to
assume that everything else follows the rule, and the rule is once
the מצוה mitzvah is done, מעילה me'ila does not apply. So therefore
by blood, if we have two ways of reading the פסוק, pasuk,
we're going to choose to read it according to the rule, and
the rule is is that is that מעילה me'ila doesn't apply after
the blood is put on the מזבח, mizbeach, and therefore the connection
of before and after will tell us it doesn't apply before as
well. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this. הניחא לרבנן דאמרי והניחם שם ללמד שטעונין גניזה, Hanicha l'rabbanan de'amri
vehinnicham sham l'lammed shete'unin genizah, that works for the rabbis that say
that that's what the הלכה halacha is by the clothes of the
כהן גדול kohen gadol on יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, that they have
to be buried, that there's still מעילה. me'ila. אלא לרבי דוסא דאמר
מותרות הן לכהן הדיוט ובלבד שלא ישתמש בהן ליום הכפורים אחר, Ella
l'Rabbi Dosa de'amar muttarot hen l'kohen hedyot uvilvad shelo yishtamesh bahen l'Yom
HaKippurim acher, actually they can be used by a normal כהן, kohen,
they just can't be used on another יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, which
is by itself a bizarre idea, right? I mean, it's like this
thing that was used in the holy of holies and went, you
know, the כהן גדול kohen gadol inside or whatever, now you use
it for like your daily עבודה. avodah. So it seems like the
point according to this is not so much that that like somehow
is a compromise of the קדושה kedusha of the בגדים, begadim, it
seems according to him the idea is is that every יום כיפור
Yom Kippur has to be unique and distinct. So you don't reuse
something from a previous יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. I'm sure there's a
good דרשה drasha there. Okay, so anyway, דאמר מותרות הן לכהן הדיוט
ובלבד שלא ישתמש בהן ליום הכפורים אחר מאי איכא למימר? de'amar muttarot
hen l'kohen hedyot uvilvad shelo yishtamesh bahen l'Yom HaKippurim acher, mai ikka
l'meimar? So according to him you don't have two exceptions, so maybe
you can have stuff that's not other things like the that maybe
the blood could be נעשית מצותו na'asit mitzvato
and still מעילה. me'ila. So the גמרא Gemara says משום דהוי
תרומת הדשן ועגלה ערופה שני כתובים הבאים כאחד וכל שני כתובים הבאים
כאחד אין מלמדין,
mishum dehavy terumat hadeshen ve'eglah arufah
shenei ketuvim habba'im ke'echad vechol shenei ketuvim habba'im ke'echad ein melammadin, because
by עגלה ערופה eglah arufah it says, you know, similarly we learn
now וערפו שם, ve'arfu sham, so the same word שם, sham, והניחם
שם vehinnicham sham like with the ושמו, vesamo, but
anyway וערפו
שם את העגלה בנחל,
ve'arfu sham et ha'eglah
banachal,
that you break its neck there which means you leave it there
and you can't benefit from it. Now, by the way, עגלה ערופה
eglah arufah is not exactly מעילה, me'ila, right? עגלה ערופה eglah arufah
is something that's נעשית מצותו na'asit mitzvato and the prohibited status still
remains, but it's not exactly an issue of מעילה. me'ila. So the
גמרא'ס Gemara's being a little bit broader, saying some there are things
that after the מצוה mitzvah was done doesn't change their status. We're
broadening the point a little bit. And therefore, since you have two
or three exceptions, we're going to assume in this classic גמרא Gemara
way, oh, once there's a lot of exceptions, nothing else is going
to be an exception. Like that's that's those are the exceptions not
the rule, and therefore for blood we're going to assume we'll fit
the rule and we'll say that after it's on the מזבח mizbeach
and נעשית מצותו na'asit mitzvato מעילה me'ila no longer applies. And since
the verse connects before and after, מעילה me'ila doesn't apply before as
well. Okay, so הניחא למאן דאמר אין מלמדין, hanicha l'man de'amar ein
melammadin, that's good if you say that
that, you know, with two פסוקים pesukim you cannot apply it. אלא
למאן דאמר מלמדין, ella l'man de'amar melammadin, but according to the opinion
that with two פסוקים pesukim it can be a rule, you need
three פסוקים pesukim for it not to be a rule. Now it's
possible you have three פסוקים pesukim here. If you have all three,
תרומת הדשן, בגדי כהונה, ועגלה ערופה, terumat hadeshen, bigdei kehuna, ve'eglah arufah,
but if you don't have בגדי כהונה, bigdei kehuna, you only have
two. So if you only have two cases of נעשית מצותו na'asit
mitzvato where the problem remains and you say that that doesn't prevent
you from applying it more broadly, you need three to not apply
it more broadly, so then you should say the same by the
blood, that the blood could maybe also be a case where the
איסור issur still remains, the status still remains even after it's put
on the מזבח. mizbeach. So the גמרא Gemara says אלא למאן דאמר
מלמדין מאי איכא למימר? ella l'man de'amar melammadin mai ikka l'meimar? תרי
מיעוטי כתיבי. terei mi'utei ketivi. Ah, it says
two extra extra letters to emphasize that these are the only exceptions
and nothing else. כתיב הכא הערופה, ketiv hacha ha'arufah, the עגלה eglah
that is ערופה, arufah, that this is the only one that remains
in this status even after the נעשית מצותו. na'asit mitzvato. This is
not a general principle. והתם כתיב vehatam ketiv and by תרומת הדשן
terumat hadeshen ושמו, vesamo, not just ושם, vesham, ושמו, vesamo, you
should put it, okay.
So therefore, there are few things that are exceptions and that the
status remains even after נעשית מצותו, na'asit mitzvato, but the פסוקים pesukim
are clear that those are either because there're two or three of
them or because of extra letters in the פסוקים pesukim that these
are that it's only by these things are the exceptions. So blood
would follow the general rule. And the general rule is once it's
on the מזבח mizbeach and נעשית מצותו, na'asit mitzvato, מעילה me'ila no
longer applies. And since the verse connects before and after, מעילה me'ila
doesn't apply before as well. So we have three ways to say
that מעילה me'ila does not apply by blood. one is I gave
it לכם lachem to you, לכפר, lechaper, it's there for כפרה, kappara,
it's not there for מעילה, me'ila,
and הוא hu before and after it's on the altar is the
same and if after on the altar there's no מעילה me'ila there's
no מעילה me'ila before it's on the altar. By the way, there's
a big תוספות Tosafot here, it's not big, medium-sized, הוא לפני כפרה
hu lifnei kappara where he's bothered because there's a classic גמרא Gemara
that sounds like there is מעילה me'ila by the blood. There's a
גמרא Gemara that talks about when the blood of the sacrifices would
like run out, you know there'd be like a, like a pipe,
not a whatever, you know a ditch that would sort of take
the blood of the sacrifices and bring it out to נחל קדרון,
Nachal Kidron, the Wadi of Kidron, and it would be sold there
to be used as fertilizer, but the, but it says there that
if you, that only after they bought it because and then they
transferred, they redeemed the sanctity of it, but before they bought it
there would actually be מעילה me'ila on the blood. So תוספות Tosafot
is very bothered, here it makes it clear there's no מעילה, me'ila,
there it sounds like there is מעילה. me'ila. He has a couple
of answers but you know, maybe it's דרבנן, derabbanan, maybe it's something
else, but anyway it's worth noting that it's not just so obvious,
you know, that there's no מעילה. me'ila. Anyway, so now because we
have three verses, that's going to allow us to teach the other
things that blood is excluded from. Right, it's a, from this idea
not just of פיגול pigul because it's a מתיר, matir, but also
נותר nosar and טמא. tamei. So blood like exists in its own
category, again quite fascinating, right? It's the מתיר, matir, it's the magic,
it's the thing that makes the thing into a קרבן, korban, nothing
else makes it into a קרבן, korban, but somehow it's so special
that none of the other, maybe it's you know, it's so, again
I think that some of this has to do with the idea
כי הדם הוא הנפש. ki hadam hu hanefesh. If it really represents
the soul, then it's distinct from any of the physical aspects of
the קרבן. korban. You know, so the same way the soul doesn't
become טמא, tamei, only physical things, right, somehow all these statuses somehow
don't adhere to the blood.
Okay, so it sounds like this.
Now,
okay,
ושלשה קראי בדם למה לי, u'slasha kray b'dam lama li, so why
do I need three פסוקים pesukim to exclude it from מעילה me'ila
to get to, to get exactly where we're trying to get? חד
למעוטי ממעילה מנותר מטומאה chad l'ma'utei mi'me'ila mi'nosar mi'tumah to exclude it
from these three categories, not although all three seem to be said
for מעילה, me'ila, we're going to say you're going to use all
three of them and you're going to exclude it from these other
categories as well. And פיגול pigul we already know. אבל פיגול לא
צריך קרא, aval pigul lo tzarich kra, פיגול pigul you don't need
a פסוק, pasuk, דתנן כל שיש לו מתיר בין לאדם בין למזבח
חייב עליו משום פיגול, d'tenan kol sheyeish lo matir bein l'adam bein
l'mizbeach chayav alav mishum pigul, so only something that has a מתיר,
matir, it itself is not a מתיר. matir. פיגול pigul applies to,
ודם גופיה מתיר הוא, v'dam gufei matir hu, and דם dam itself
is a מתיר matir and פיגול pigul doesn't apply to a lot
of things because of that principle. Okay.
אמר רבי יוחנן שלשה כריתות בשלמים למה לי? amar Rabi Yochanan slasha
krisos b'shlamim lama li?
Now למה? lama? So by the שלמים shlamim
it says,
right, it
says by the טומאה, tumah, and we had this once before where
we were trying to figure out what is the, you know whether
this middle פסוק, pasuk, when it speaks about being טמא tamei and
eating קדשים, kodashim, is it talking that you're טמא tamei or that
the קדשים kodashim are טמא. tamei. You might remember that from a
little while ago. So it says like this, it says in במדבר,
Bamidbar, ויקרא כ"ב, Vayikra chaf beis, אמור אליהם לדרתיכם כל איש אשר
יקרב מכל זרעכם אל הקדשים אשר יקדישו בני ישראל לה' וטמאתו עליו
ונכרתה
emor aleihem l'doroseichem kol ish asher yikrav
mikol zar'achem el hakodashim asher yakdishu b'nei Yisrael l'Hashem v'tumaso alav v'nichresa
so that's one כרת, kareis, הנפש ההיא מלפני ה'. hanefesh hahi milifnei
Hashem. Okay, and number two, איש איש מזרע אהרן והוא צרוע או
זב בקדשים לא יאכל עד אשר יטהר והנגע בכל טמא נפש,
ish ish mizeira Aharon v'hu tzarua o zav bakodashim lo yochal ad
asher yit'har v'hanogea b'chol tmei nefesh, okay, או איש וגו' אשר תצא
ממנו שכבת זרע, o ish etc. asher teitzei mimenu shichvas zera, או
איש אשר יגע בכל שרץ וגו' o ish asher yiga b'chol sheretz
etc. לנפש אשר תגע בו וטמאה עד הערב ולא יאכל מן הקדשים
וגו' lanefesh asher tiga bo v'tam'ah ad ha'erev v'lo yochal min hakodashim
etc. וגו' וגו' etc. etc. wait hold on, hold on I just
missed that.
One minute, where's the other one?
או איש אשר יגע בלא o ish asher yiga b'lo
no
but where is it כרת? kareis? Hold on, am I in the
right place? One minute. 7:20 it's 7:21.
Oh I'm in the wrong place. 7, I'm sorry.
Yes, thank you. Okay I don't know what yeah, I was looking
I looked at wrong, fine. Okay so it says like this, it
says, והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל באש ישרף והבשר כל
טהור יאכל בשר v'habasar asher yiga b'chol tamei lo ye'achel ba'eish yisaref
v'habasar kol tahor yochal basar והנפש אשר תאכל בשר מזבח השלמים אשר
לה' וטמאתו עליו ונכרתה הנפש ההיא מעמיה, v'hanefesh asher tochal basar mizevach
hashlamim asher l'Hashem v'tumaso alav v'nichresa hanefesh hahi mei'ameha,
so that's כרת kareis and we said that verse וטמאתו עליו v'tumaso
alav is a little vague but we said it means you're טמא
tamei not the meat is טמא. tamei. Okay so if you're טמא
tamei and you eat the שלמים shlamim you get כרת. kareis. And
then the next verse 7:21, ונפש כי תגע בכל טמא v'nefesh ki
siga b'chol tamei and we said תגע tiga means eat, בטומאת אדם
וגו' b'tum'as adam etc. etc. I'm sorry, I keep on I'm sorry
I'm confusing, anyway. No you touch something טמא tamei או בבהמה טמאה
או בכל שקץ טמא ואכל מזבח השלמים אשר לה' ונכרתה, o b'vhema
tmei'ah o b'chol sheketz tamei v'achal mizevach hashlamim asher l'Hashem v'nichresa, so
that's two כריתות krisos right next to each other when you're טמא
tamei in ויקרא ז' כ' ו-כ"א. Vayikra zayin chaf v'chaf aleph.
And then later, right, in ויקרא כ"ב, Vayikra chaf beis, that's what
I was starting with, it says, כל איש אשר יקרב kol ish
asher yikrav and here we say יקרב yikrav means eat, מכל זרעכם
אל הקדשים אשר יקדישו וטמאתו עליו ונכרתה. mikol zar'achem el hakodashim asher
yakdishu v'tumaso alav v'nichresa. Okay
so three times. Twice in ויקרא ז', Vayikra zayin, once in ויקרא
כ"ב. Vayikra chaf beis. as you get כרת kares for eating if
you're טמא. tamei. So why do you need all three? אחת לכלל
ואחת לפרט, achas l'chlal v'achas l'ferat,
one for a general point, one for to limit it. Now that
sounds like it's saying כלל ופרט klal u'prat and sounds like it's
actually the point is to limit. But actually both רש״י Rashi and
תוספות Tosfos say that's not what פרט prat here means. פרט prat
here means the principle, it really the more accurate phrase is דבר
שהיה בכלל ויצא מן הכלל ללמד לא ללמד על עצמו יצא אלא
ללמד על הכלל כולו יצא. Davar shehayah bichlal veyatza min haklal lilamed
lo lilamed al atzmo yatza ela lilamed al haklal kulo yatza. This
is one of the principles that if you had something that was
just, you know, a general הלכה halacha and then it was some
singled out, it's teaching you this thing that we're singling out for
shouldn't be applied just to this, but to the more like general,
the whole class that it's a part of. So what it really
is a way of saying is that even though the פסוקים psukim
are talking about שלמים, shelamim, since it repeats it by שלמים shelamim
again, it's really telling you that this is true about all sacrifices,
it's not limited to שלמים. shelamim. Okay.
So it's a funny way of saying it, but the point is,
one is to tell you by שלמים, shelamim, one is to repeat
it by שלמים shelamim to tell you it really applies to all
sacrifices. ואחת לדברים שאינם נאכלים. ve'achas lidvarim she'einam ne'echalim. And the third
one is to tell you that it applies even things that are
not edible. That if you're טמא tamei and you eat something that
is inedible but it's a sanctified, like the קטורת ketores for example
and the קומץ kometz and this type of stuff, okay, nevertheless you
would get כרת, kares, which is a pretty big חידוש. chiddush.
Okay so,
ולרבי שמעון דאמר דברים שאינם נאכלים אין חייבין עליהם, u'le'Rabbi Shimon d'amar
dvarim she'einam ne'echalim ein chayavin aleihem, but you might remember from yesterday
in the משנה, Mishnah, the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon actually said if
it's not edible you don't get כרת. kares. So why do you
need another פסוק pasuk for
כרת? kares? אין חייבין עליהם משום טומאה. ein chayavin aleihem mishum tumah.
לאתויי מאי? l'asuyei mai? So what's this extra third פסוק pasuk tell
you? לאתויי חטאת הפנימיות l'asuyei chatas hapnimiyos to tell you that you
get כרת kares if you're טמא tamei even if you eat the
meat of a inner חטאת chatas
or maybe the אימורים emurim of an inner
חטאת. chatas. סלקא דעתך אמינא הוה אמר רבי שמעון כל שאינו מזבח
חיצון כשלמים אין חייבין עליו משום פיגול. salik da'atach amina hava amar
Rabbi Shimon kol she'eino mizbe'ach chitzon kishlamim ein chayavin alav mishum pigul.
So since רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says that the inner חטאת chatas
is excluded from פיגול pigul because the blood doesn't go on the
outer מזבח, mizbe'ach, so once it's excluded from פיגול pigul I might
think
משום טומאה נמי לא ליחייבי mishum tumah nami lo lechayvei קמשמע לן
kamashmalan that you are. Okay so you have three פסוקים psukim about
being טמא tamei and getting כרת kares when you eat the קרבנות
korbanot to tell you it applies to שלמים, shelamim, it applies to
all קרבנות, korbanot, and it applies to even things that are inedible
that are sanctified for the מזבח. mizbe'ach. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
that says that things that are inedible you are not חייב, chayav,
on
for him it would be emphasizing that you're חייב chayav even for
the inner חטאות chata'ot even though he excludes the inner חטאות chata'ot
from פיגול. pigul. Alright so now we turn to the actual statement
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
in
exactly this debate of are you חייב chayav כרת kares for when
you're טמא tamei and you eat inedible things that are put on
the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
נומי רבי שמעון. numi Rabbi Shimon. נומי numi is a old you
know Mishnaic term like a term that means said, said רבי שמעון.
Rabbi Shimon. I don't know why it's used sometimes. But anyway, נומי
רבי שמעון, numi Rabbi Shimon, so רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon said,
מחייב בדבר שדרכו לאכול אבל עצים... mechayev b'davar shedarko l'echol aval eitzim...
מחייב mechayev doesn't fit with נומי numi that he said, but anyway,
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon anyway רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would only be
מחייב mechayev something, only say you get כרת kares if it's normally
eaten but if it's something that's not edible you don't get כרת
kares for eating it when you're טמא. tamei. Says the גמרא, Gemara,
איתמר, itmar, was taught.
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish.
Debate of
רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש. Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish. רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי
ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina. So there's these two
sets of these two rabbis, חד מהאי זוזא וחד מהאי זוזא, chad
mehai zuza v'chad mehai zuza, he tried to say זוגא. zuga. Anyway,
so you know, there's group A it consists of רבי יוחנן וריש
לקיש Rabbi Yochanan v'Resh Lakish and there's group B it consists of
רבי אלעזר ורבי יוסי ברבי חנינא. Rabbi Elazar v'Rabbi Yose b'Rabbi Chanina.
So one member of group A and one member of group B
hold a certain position, and the other member of group A and
the other member of group B hold another position, just we don't
know. So there are how many possibilities are there? I guess there's
two possibilities of the groupings and four possibilities of what they hold
because anyway, okay, so, anyway, so they debate the following.
חד אמר, chad amar, one says, מחלוקת בטומאת בשר, machlokes b'tumas basar,
that the debate is when the meat is טמא, tamei, okay, and
there and they're debating whether when the meat is טמא tamei then
it's only a לאו, lav, a simple negative prohibition, it's not כרת.
kares. Okay so and the reason that, let me just point it
out, the reason that that's more of a reason to think that
טומאה tumah would apply even though it's inedible is again in one
of the more ironic דרשות, drashos, the פסוק pasuk is והבשר אשר
יגע בכל טמא לא יאכל,
v'habasar asher yiga
b'chol tamei lo ye'achel, so we say oh הבשר habasar though actually
it's probably the
ו', vav, ו, ve, or to say that even means inedible
things. לרבות עצים ולבונה l'rabos eitzim u'levonah to include wood and the
frankincense. So that's when the thing is
טמא, tamei, אשר יגע... asher yiga... So there's more reason to think
that people would agree, or there's more reason to think that when
the thing is טמא tamei because of this דרשה, drashah, that it
would be a problem even if it's inedible. Okay, so let's see
how they were debating the scope of this debate of
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So חד אמר chad amar מחלוקת בטומאת בשר,
machloket b'tumat basar,
that the debate is about when the meat is טמא tamei because
there there might be a פסוק pasuk to say that you're חייב
chayav at least מלקות malkot even if it's inedible. אבל בטומאת הגוף
aval b'tumat haguf when you're טמא, tamei,
since there's no פסוק, pasuk, דברי הכל אין לוקה, divrei hakol ein
loke, even the rabbis would agree with רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that
you don't get lashes because it's a little crazy to say that
you transgress when it's something that's inedible. Okay, so the most the
rabbis would say it would be when the meat is טמא tamei
because of this דרשה. drashah. That's what one group says. וחד אמר
v'chad amar and the other says כמחלוקת בזו כך מחלוקת בזו. k'machloket
b'zo kach machloket b'zo. No, they debate both of them. מאי טעמא
mai ta'ama why?
Since the חידוש chidush is only in this פסוק, pasuk, why would
the rabbis say that you also are חייב chayav when you're טמא
tamei and the stuff is inedible? Because the two ideas are linked.
כיון דקרינן ביה והבשר אשר יגע בכל טמא, kevan d'karinan bei v'habasar
asher yiga b'chol tamei, since this פסוק pasuk when the thing is
טמא, tamei, the ו vav comes to include inedible things, so קרינן
ביה וטומאתו עליו, karinan bei v'tumat alav, it's also linked to the
next פסוק pasuk that's juxtaposed with it that speaks about when you're
טמא. tamei. Okay, so basically we say one version is that everybody
agrees when you're טמא tamei you're not חייב chayav if it's inedible,
it's only when the thing is טמא tamei and that's כרת. kares.
The only debate is when it's טמא tamei and it's a לאו
lav because of this פסוק. pasuk. And the other approach says, no,
the same rabbis that would say you're חייב chayav in this case
would say that once it's true in this case, it's true in
the other case of טומאה tumah as well. That's one version of
the debate of the debate. And here's another version of the debate.
Okay. רב טביומי מתני הכי, Rav Tavyumi matni hachi, that's how רב
טביומי Rav Tavyumi teaches this debate of these אמוראים amoraim how to
interpret
what רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and the חכמים chachamim are debating. רב
כהנא מתני הכי, Rav Kahana matni hachi, but here's how רב כהנא
Rav Kahana teaches it. חד
מהאי זוזא וחד מהאי זוזא, chad mehai zuza v'chad mehai zuza, הסיפא,
ha'seifa, that that's going on not limiting
the scope of the rabbis but debating the scope for רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon who says that you're פטור. patur. חד אמר chad amar
מחלוקת בטומאת הגוף, machloket b'tumat haguf, אבל בטומאת בשר דברי הכל לוקה,
aval b'tumat basar divrei hakol loke, one says that the flip, I
mean it's the same idea that this is more obvious, but this
says oh this when the meat is, when the thing is טמא
tamei even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon agrees that you're חייב. chayav. That's
because of the second this דרשה. drashah. Okay, the question is where
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says you're פטור patur is for כרת kares
when you're טמא. tamei. But for the לאו lav when the thing
is טמא tamei even רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon would say that you're
חייב. chayav. And the other one says וחד אמר v'chad amar כמחלוקת
בזו כך מחלוקת בזו. k'machloket b'zo kach machloket b'zo. No, it's the
same debate. אמר רבא amar Rava מסתברא כמאן דאמר כמחלוקת בזו כך
מחלוקת בזו, mistabra k'man d'amar k'machloket b'zo kach machloket b'zo,
it makes sense that if רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is going to
exempt you when you're טמא, tamei, he's also going to exempt you
when the meat is טמא, tamei, when the thing is טמא. tamei.
מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama? כיון דלא קרינן ביה וטומאתו עליו ונכרתה, kevan
d'lo karinan bei v'tuma'ato alav v'nichrata, לא קרינן ביה והבשר אשר יגע
בכל טמא לא יאכל. lo karinan bei v'habasar asher yiga b'chol tamei
lo ye'achel.
Same thing except the reverse. Okay, so either you say if you're
going to say that this case you're חייב chayav when the thing
is טמא, tamei, then it makes sense that you should say according
that let's say that you're חייב chayav when you're טמא tamei
because the טומאות tumot are linked. Or go the reverse way. If
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon exempts you when you're טמא, tamei, then it
makes sense he would also exempt you when the thing is טמא.
tamei. Okay, so we have all these different possibilities about what exactly
is the scope of the debate.
And the גמרא Gemara ends והא אמר מר והבשר לרבות עצים
ולבונה. v'ha amar mar v'habasar l'rabbot etzim v'levonah. One minute, but how
could anybody say you know that when the meat, when the thing
is טמא tamei
you're exempt, how could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say that you're exempt
in both cases? Don't we have a classic דרשה drashah to say
that this includes inedible things? So how could רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
say you're exempt? So the גמרא Gemara says פסולה בעלמא, psula b'alma,
that's only פסולה בעלמא, psula b'alma, that's only
rabbinic that you shouldn't use it after it became טמא tamei or
whatever, it's a rabbinic problem, it's not really a biblical one. Okay,
so basically it's a very bizarre idea you have to admit that
you're חייב chayav for eating something that is
inedible. And it's not just misusing it, it's specifically eating it, so
it's quite bizarre. You know maybe it has something to do I'm
just thinking right now that so much of our מעילה me'ilah discussion
has been comparing אכילת מזבח achilat mizbe'ach to אכילת אדם, achilat adam,
you know and the idea of eating means not just I'm going
to eat it at the wrong time, I'm going to put it
on the מזבח mizbe'ach at the wrong time, so maybe because this
is considered edible by the מזבח, mizbe'ach, you know the מזבח mizbe'ach
consumes it, maybe therefore what I do to it is considered that
I'm doing an act of eating even though normally it wouldn't be
an act of eating. So just occurred to me that that might
be דווקא davka why we have this in the one case of
things that go on the מזבח, mizbe'ach, that eating something inedible. at
that, you know, towns. Anyway, so רב שמעון Rav Shimon says it
doesn't, and then the question is what is the scope of the
debate? It's clear that when the thing is טמא, tamei, there's a
דרשה, drasha, so there's more reason to think that that's a case
that everybody agrees is a problem. But again, that's the question here
about are they arguing on both or they only arguing on one
of them, and if only one, which one? Okay.
Now we move on to the next משנה. mishnah. And actually this
משנה, mishnah, finally,
somebody could have argued that this משנה mishnah might have maybe should
have been the first משנה mishnah of the מסכת masechet actually, or
the whole next פרק perek might maybe should have been the first
פרק perek of the מסכת. masechet. The next פרק perek is איזהו
מקומן. Eizehu Mekoman. So for people who say that in your morning,
you know, whatever,
דאוונען, davening, so that really is a nice clear laying out of
all the things, whatever. So these are some, you know, we started
everything with all these invalidities, and now we're going to sort of
talk about here's the right way to do it. Okay? So it's
funny the way מסכתות masechtos sometimes are organized that way. It just
shows you that they're not talking to the uninitiated. They're like talking
to the rabbinic class and therefore you want to say the interesting
stuff first. Oh, what happens if it's this problem or that problem,
whatever. The basic rules we'll get to later. Anyway, so here's let's
see this משנה mishnah that ends this פרק. perek. לשם ששה דברים
הזבח נזבח. Leshem shisha devarim hazevach nizbach.
The קרבן korban is sacrificed for six things, meaning presumably, although only
certain thoughts or statements invalidate it, at least you're supposed to have
six things in mind. Okay, nobody says it if you didn't actively
have these in mind it's invalid, but at least this is what
you're supposed to be thinking. לשם זבח, Leshem zevach,
that it should be a sacrifice, okay, meaning but that means that
it should be the right thing. If it's an עולה, olah, you
should realize that it's an עולה, olah, you shouldn't think that it's
a שלמים, shelamim, which basically gets back to like our first משנה,
mishnah, that when you're שינוי שמו, shinui shemo, like when you have
a כוונה kavannah for a different קרבן. korban. Okay, לשם זובח, leshem
zoveach,
for the owner. So that's שינוי בעלים. shinui be'alim. Don't have an
intent for the wrong owner. Having intent for the right קרבן korban
and the right owner, those are things that we've talked about. לשם
השם, Leshem Hashem, knowing that this is being offered to God. Oh,
there's an idea. Okay, we haven't mentioned God too much. לשם אשים,
Leshem ishim, knowing that there is going to be a part that's
going to be offered up on the altar, burnt. לשם ריח, Leshem
reiach, that it will be actually a smell will go up, ריח
ניחוח. reiach nichoach. לשם ניחוח, Leshem nichoach, and it'll be a pleasing
smell. Now that's all very interesting, right? All of this is like
completely different than the focus that we've been having until now. Right,
here it's sort of much more like relational, like you're thinking about
the קרבן korban like I said sort of more like the narratives
in the תורה. Torah. Somebody is bringing it, offering it to God.
There's, you know, there's the offeror, there's God, there's you want it
to go up, you want it to be a ריח ניחוח. reiach
nichoach. The idea of the כוונה, kavannah, intent, like you know, in
sort of it's all very much speaks to that like relational aspect
that we really have not been dealing with at all, you know?
And you really like like, you know, it's it's like where you
find, other than the things of שינוי השם shinui Hashem and שינוי
בעלים, shinui be'alim, to find that there's really problems with these other
four and they create technical problems, like you really don't find, you
know? And therefore this is really like framing I think a more
how a קרבן korban really looks from the perspective of the one
who's offering it,
you know? And as I said like all these relational aspects of
it. Okay.
וחטאת ואשם לשם חטא. Vechatas ve'asham leshem cheit. And the חטאת chatas
אשם asham has to be for the sake of the sin, the
specific sin it's being brought for. אמר רבי יוסי, Amar Rabbi Yose,
said רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yose, אף מי שלא היה בלבו לשם אחד
מכל אלו כשר. af mi shelo hayah belibo leshem echad mikol elu
kasher. Even if you weren't thinking about any of these things, it's
כשר. kasher. שהוא תנאי בית דין, Shehu tenai beis din, that it
is a stipulation of the court, שאין המחשבה הולכת אלא אחר העובד,
she'ein hamachshavah holeches ela achar ha'oved, because the thought only goes by
the worshiper. Now what the heck does the last line have to
do with the previous line? Right, he just said you don't have
to actively think about it. We're like predefining that we're going to
say that any סתם stam offering of it is implicitly for these
things, and it's only a problem when you actively have a different
thought. That's like the opening סוגיא sugya of the מסכת masechet about
סתם לשמה. stam lishmah. So that's an important principle. You know, unless
you actively think otherwise you haven't invalidated it and that's how we're
going to sort of what we're going to how we're going to
frame things. What does it have to do with מחשבה machshavah only
goes after the עובד? oved? What what's the relevance of that? So
רש"י Rashi says it's like a additional point. By the way, don't
think that you the owner can invalidate it if you think something
actively wrong. No, it's all like A, it's not going to be
invalid if it wasn't actively being thought because we think that even
if you have no active thought it's okay, סתם לשמה. stam lishmah.
And number two, don't think if you the owner had a wrong
thought you're going to invalidate it because it doesn't go by the
owner, it goes by, you know, it goes by the כהן kohen
who's bringing it.
But then it's really two unconnected statements. So there's two other interesting
reads of this last line, which I want to just make you
appreciate. Okay, so read number one is רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose is
saying two things. Number one is סתמא לשמה lishmah *stama lishma*, you
don't have to actively think it. And number two is the owner's
thoughts don't invalidate, which then presumably isn't debated; maybe presumably like everybody
agrees to that. Version number two that רמב״ם Rambam *Rambam* in פירוש
המשניות *Peirush HaMishnayos* suggests is he suggests that the first opinion is
actually implicitly assuming that the owner's thoughts invalidate it. And then רבי
שמעון *Rebbi Shimon* is saying, okay, that no, because it's not the
owner's, it's the כהן's *Kohen's* thoughts. And you know why? Because if
it was the owner's thoughts we'd have a real problem, because if
it was the owner's thoughts, the owner could invalidate it and we
wouldn't have control over that, you know? And therefore so we read
רבי יוסי *Rebbi Yosi* to be saying אף מי שלא היה בלבו
אחד מכל אלו כשר kasher שהיא תנאי בית דין שאין המחשבה הולכת
אלא אחר עובד *Af mi shelo haya belibo echad mikol elu kasher
shehi tnai Beis Din she'ein hamachshava holeches ela achar oved*. So it's
not so much a point about סתמא לשמה lishmah *stama lishma*, but
like it's like even if you the owner, אף מי שלא היה
בלבו *af mi shelo haya belibo*, he's not saying סתמא *stama*. He's
saying if you the owner didn't have these thoughts or even had
wrong thoughts, okay, it doesn't matter because it's not about your thoughts,
it's about the כהן's *Kohen's* thoughts. So that's a very interesting read
which makes a—really gives a possibility that that's—that at least the תנא
קמא *Tanna Kamma* or somebody out there held that it's the owner's
thoughts that matter, which obviously we have never said in the מסכת
*masechet*. A third read which is maybe the best, okay, and it's—and
it sort of seems to be corroborated by the תוספתא *Tosefta*, is
that what does the word הזבח נזבח *hazevach nizbach* mean? What's נזבח
*nizbach*? What act is נזבח *nizbach*?
לזבוח *lizboach* is to שחט *shacht*. Okay, and עובד *oved*, classic word
of עובד *oved*, the עבודה *avoda*, right? Remember who can do שחיטה
shechitah *shechita*? Anybody, not a כהן *Kohen*. So there's a question is
שחיטה shechitah עבודה לאו עבודה *shechita avoda lav avoda* etc., so עבודה
*avoda* is the blood stuff that's not the שחיטה shechita *shechita*. And
that the תנא קמא *Tanna Kamma* held it goes by the שוחט
*shochet*, and that רבי יוסי *Rebbi Yosi* holds it goes by the
guy who—the כהן *Kohen* who's doing the blood. And you might remember
at the very beginning of the מסכת *masechet* when we wanted to
prove issues of שלא לשמו shelo lishmo *shelo lishmo*, a lot of
the פסוקים *pesukim* we had were by the שחיטה *shechita*. And then
we said oh that's all good by the שחיטה *shechita*, how do
you know it applies to the זריקה *zerika*? And we had to
quote another פסוק *pasuk*, how do you know it applies to the
קבלה *kabala* and the הולכה *holacha*? So when you read that, you
also—we sort of all—we sort of thought it was all pro forma,
oh it just applies by everything. But really what that might be
doing is it might actually be coming to level out an actual
debate that existed. There might have been those that held that fundamentally
the מחשבה *machshava* was by the שוחט *shochet*, and others held that
fundamentally it was by the כהן *Kohen*. And I want to say
something, this is not so different from the first approach that the
מחשבה *machshava* goes by the owners. Because remember if the כהנים *Kohanim*
only began at the time of the קבלת הדם *kabbalas hadam*, now
I don't know in practice whether they took over the שחיטה *shechita*
or not, but assuming they didn't take over the שחיטה *shechita*, who
do you think was doing the שחיטה *shechita*? The owners, right? Assuming
that people I guess at that time everybody knew how to שחט
*shacht* animals or whatever. So therefore that would be saying it's true
if the owner is at home and has some thought, it can't
invalidate because you know it's just a random thought. It has to
be—sort of have traction and be concretized and be part of the
עבודה *avoda*. But still, there might have been those that say it's
the שוחט's *shochet's* thoughts who matter, which is going to situate a
lot more relationship and power in terms of the owner. And then
comes along רבי יוסי *Rebbi Yosi* and he says no, you can't
trust the owners; תנאי בית דין *tnai Beis Din* who that it's
not going to go by the שוחט *shochet*, it's only going to
go by the עובד *oved*, it's only going to go by the
כהנים *Kohanim*. Okay, so that's very interesting. In the end we say
it goes both by the שחיטה *shechita* and by the other עבודות
*avodos*. Okay, so very interesting ways of possibly reading this. Again, the
traditional way to read it is he's just making the point of
סתמא לשמה lishmo. *stama lishma* and to sort of bracket that last
statement in—in you know in the משנה Mishnah *mishna* as a somewhat
superfluous statement. Okay, let's take a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*.
אמר רב Rav יהודה אמר רב Rav *Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav*.
Okay,
so now we're going to דרשן *darshan* the פסוק *pasuk*, עולה olah
היא אשי ריח ניחוח להשם reyach nichoach l'Hashem *Olah hi ishei reiach
nichoach l'Hashem*.
Okay. So what was he saying? In the end we don't accept
this last statement, right?
What do you mean we don't accept it? We do accept that
סתמא לשמה lishmo. *stama lishma*.
No, I mean about...
We do accept that the owner's thoughts don't invalidate. What?
The last statement about it's determined only by the one who does
the עבודה *avoda*?
Well, it depends what... yeah, meaning...
well to the degree we say that, we say it means the
one who does the עבודה *avoda* and not the owners, but עבודה
*avoda* would include שחיטה *shechita*. Okay, meaning the way I framed it,
maybe the debate was עבודה *avoda* versus שחיטה *shechita*. To the degree
that we're going to read this last line in the משנה *mishna*
as a דברי הכל *divrei hakol*, as a consensus, then we're going
to say the word עבודה *avoda* includes שחיטה *shechita* but it's to
exclude owners when they're not doing an עבודה *avoda*. עולה היא אשי
ריח ניחוח reyach nichoach להשם l'Hashem, *Olah hi ishei reiach nichoach l'Hashem*.
Okay,
so that's going to tell us all the things you sacrifice—you have
in mind when you sacrifice it. עולה לשם עולה leshem olah? *Olah
leshem Olah*. So עולה *Olah* is the לשמה *lishma* of the קרבן
korban *korban*. What קרבן korban. *korban* is it for? לאפוקי לשם שלמים
leshem shelamim דלא *L'afokei leshem shelamim d'lo*, which is our first issue
in the משנה *mishna*, שלא לשמו *shelo lishmo* for a different קרבן
korban. *korban*. אשים *ishim* or אשה *isheh*, לשם leshem, אשים *leshem ishim*.
You have to have. mind that it's going to be something that's
going to be put on the fire, לאפוקי כבבא דלא,
which is to exclude a case where you're basically going to plan
on just putting it on a, you know, you're on like embers,
like you know on a, on a charcoal, you know, you have
to have intent that you're going to put it on an actual
live flame fire. ריח לשם ריח, Reyach l'shem Reyach,
that you want that it should be done in a way that
raises up the smoke. לאפוקי אברים לאפוקי אברים שצלאן, l'afukei evarim l'afukei
evarim she'tslaan,
don't pre-pre-roast them before putting them on the altar because then the
smells only come when you put the raw meat on the altar.
Okay, והעלן דלא דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב אברים שצלאן והעלן אין
בהם משום ריח ניחוח. ve-hellan d'lo d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav evarim
she'tslaan ve-hellan ein bahem mishum reyach nichoach. You don't satisfy ריח ניחוח
reyach nichoach. if you pre-roasted it. Now again, the קרבן korban. is
still כשר kasher, because that's all dependent on the blood. Okay, but
you didn't satisfy and he never says you have to take the
meat off the altar if you do it this way, but it
didn't satisfy the idea of ריח reyach ניחוח. nichoach, So everything that's
not the לשמה and the לשם בעלים, leshem ba'alim, this ריח reyach
ניחוח nichoach, להשם etcetera is all sort of, you know, value-added, but
it's not necessarily determines, you know, the legitimacy of the קרבן. korban,
אין בהם משום ריח, ein bahem mishum reyach, excuse me, ניחוח, nichoach.
pleasing, לשם נחת רוח להשם. leshem nachat ruach l'Hashem.
Oh, I'm doing this to for, you know, to make God happy.
Okay, which is funny, right? You know, and but we're separating notice
by the way the ריח and the ניחוח, which is part of
this whole problem of the anthropomorphisms, right? It's like וירח השם את
ריח הניחוח בינוח, vayarach Hashem et reyach hanichoach beNoach, you know, so
it was, you know, that can get to be a little anthropomorphic.
רמב״ם actually says in מורה נבוכים Moreh Nevuchim that even with the
anthropomorphisms, the only attributes that the תורה Torah ascribes in terms of
the sensory attributes to God are seeing and smelling. It never ascribes
to God, you know, touch or taste—no, hearing, I'm sorry, seeing, smelling,
and hearing, but never touch and taste. Why not? Because he says
all those three are done at a distance. That's a very interesting
insight, right? So whereas touch and taste are not. Anyway, but still,
it's pretty anthropomorphic. Somehow God smelling is a lot more anthropomorphic in
our eyes, I think, than God hearing or God seeing. So the
גמרא separates the ריח from the ניחוח. It's not that the smoke
is pleasing to God, it should bring, it should rise up smoke
and the sacrifice should be serving God's will. The sacrifice should be
לשם נחת רוח. leshem nachat ruach. Okay, להשם,
לשם, it should have, you should have God in mind. Okay, לשם
מי שאמר והיה העולם, leshem mi she'amar ve-haya ha-olam, excuse me, in
the name of the one who said and the world was created,
you should be done for the sake of God. I'm not exactly
sure how that's different than the נחת רוח, nachat ruach, but okay.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב חטאת ששחטה, amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav
Chattat she-shechat-ah, now that we're done with that, that's basically the full
extent you have of those various attributes, meaning as I said, the
things that from the perspective of the offerer, you know, if you
read all the stories in the תורה, Torah, you put it on
the altar לריח ניחוח, l'reyach nichoach, God smell—but from the perspective of
the offerer are just given like a one-minute lip service and then
we get back to what really matters, right? You know, the blood
and לשמה and לשם בעלים leshem ba'alim and so on. Okay, anyway,
so now let's get to those technical issues.
Okay, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב חטאת ששחטה לשם עולה פסולה לשם
חולין כשרה.
amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav Chattat she-shechat-ah
leshem olah psula leshem chullin keshera. When you shecht something שלא לשמה,
shelo lishmah, it only invalidates it if it's for the intent of
a different קרבן. korban If you shechted it and treated it like
חולין, chullin, that's so out of the ballpark that it doesn't invalidate.
It's such an irrelevant thought.
אמר אלעזר מאי טעמא דרב, amar Elazar mai ta'ama d'Rav, what's the
reason? ולא יחללו את קדשי בני ישראל. velo yechalelu et kodshei benei
Yisrael. קדשי מחלין קדשין. kodshi me-chalin kodshin. Okay, so the sanctified ones,
you know, desecrate the other sanctified. So it's a relevant thought to
think of another קרבן. korban ואין חולין מחלין קדשין. ve-ein chullin me-chalin
kodshin. Thinking about something
completely unsanctified is an irrelevant thought and doesn't have that effect. So
מתיב רבה. mative Rabba. So Rabba challenges. אמר רבי יוסי אף מי
שלא היה בלבו אלא לשם אחד מכל אלו כשר שהוא תנאי בית
דין. amar Rabbi Yossi af mi shelo haya belibo ela leshem echad
mikol elu kasher shehu t'nai beit din. Even if you weren't thinking
of anything, it's kosher. Okay, טעמא שלא היה בלבו כלל. ta'ama shelo
haya belibo klal. It sounds like because you had no thought.
הא היה בלבו לשם חולין פסול. ha haya belibo leshem chullin pasul.
Presumably it would mean that any wrong thought would
invalidate, even if it wasn't about a different קרבן, korban. even if
it was about חולין. chullin. Now, I don't know, you know, that's
reading a lot into silence, but anyway, that's his challenge. So it
sounds like anything worse than silence would be a problem.
אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, no, דילמא לא היה כלל כשר
ומרצה. dilma lo haya klal kasher u-meratzeh. No, maybe we should read
it this way: if you had no thought, it's both כשר, kasher,
the meat can be eaten, and it's מרצה, meratzeh, which remember means
it counts for the owner. הא היה בלבו לשם חולין כשר ואינו
מרצה.
ha haya belibo leshem
chullin kasher ve-eino meratzeh. Maybe if it was לשם חולין, leshem chullin,
maybe the קרבן korban would be כשר, kasher... it just wouldn't be
מרצה, meratzeh, it wouldn't be עולה לבעלים לשם חובה. ola l'ba'alim leshem
chova. So the problem with that is
that that presumably is in general the הלכה halacha about something that's
שחטה שלא לשמה, shechat-ah shelo lishmah, right? Something שחטה שלא לשמה, shechat-ah
shelo lishmah, the meat is
כשר... kosher you know sort of he wants to say you say
it's כשר kosher when it's לשם חולין leshem chulin this implies that
it's פסול pasul and the answer is no no no it's כשר
kosher it's just not מרצה. mirtzeh. But כשר kosher and not מרצה
mirtzeh seems to be like the point of the first משנה that
anything that's שלא לשמו is כשר אלא שלא עלו לבעלים לשם חובה.
kosher ella shelo alu labalim leshem chovah. So that's just as פסול
pasul as an עולה לשם שלמים olah leshem shelamim as an עולה
לשם חובה. olah leshem chovah. So I don't know I didn't see
an answer to that I didn't see that discussed. Do you have
your English say anything about that?
No.
So you implied the answer. It could be it doesn't really mean
that
maybe אינו מרצה eino mirtzeh doesn't really mean לא עלו לבעלים lo
alu labalim it just means like it's not ideal.
No I think you might just be saying you're reading the line
to silence. Who said that you're reading the silence means
that
but either way he's conceding that it might mean that it's אינו
מרצה. eino mirtzeh. But according to the פשיטא peshitah that לשם חולין
leshem chulin is better than לשם שלמים leshem shelamim well לשם שלמים
it's כשר ואינו מרצה kosher ve-eino mirtzeh so לשם חולין leshem chulin
has to be כשר לגמרי. kosher legamre.
I'm not sure. Anyway אמר רב אלעזר. Amar Rav Elazar. What?
Would the owner eat that meat?
Let me see if there's...
yeah right there. Would the owner eat that meat if it's not
really... it didn't perform the atonement that he was trying to receive?
So it says he has to bring another one.
Right one minute.
Yeah that's completely unhelpful. It says basically says yeah even when we
were saying לשם חולין leshem chulin it's כשר kosher we just meant
that it's not עלו לבעלים. alu labalim. But then how is that
more כשר kosher than לשם עולה? I don't understand. Anyway I'm sorry
what was your question?
Could he actually eat that meat?
Yeah he could eat the meat and it's not עלו לבעלים alu
labalim you know okay but anyway but again then it's just as
פסול pasul as anything else. Anyway now we continue.
Oh no I'm sorry that's the answer excuse me because רב Rav
was talking about a חטאת. chatat. חטאת שלא לשמו chatat shelo lishmo
that's the point okay. חטאת שלא לשמו chatat shelo lishmo is ממש
פסול. mamash pasul. Remember חטאת chatat and a פסח pesach are ממש
פסול. mamash pasul. So that's the point okay. So a חטאת לשם
עולה chatat leshem olah is פסול לגמרי pasul legamre okay and it's
not and you can't eat the meat and so on because that's
a חטאת שלא לשמו. chatat shelo lishmo. A חטאת לשם חולין chatat
leshem chulin the meat can be eaten but it's not עלו לבעלים
לשם חובה. alu labalim leshem chovah. So that's how this inhabits this
middle space. Okay let's continue this. אמר רב
אלעזר חטאת ששחטה לשם חולין כשירה. Amar Rav Elazar chatat she-shachtah leshem
chulin kesherah. Now we're going to make another distinction. So that's why
we're always talking about a חטאת chatat because the חטאת chatat is
the example that it's ממש פסול. mamash pasul. So if a חטאת
chatat was shechted because it was believed to be חולין chulin it's
כשר kosher okay so I'm sorry the opposite that you know it
was a חטאת chatat and you intentionally shechted it for the sake
of חולין. chulin. So that's like רב's Rav statement okay. If you're
trying to change its identity but you have in mind חולין chulin
it's כשר kosher. meaning it's not עלו לבעלים alu labalim like we
just said but it's not פסול pasul like a חטאת שלא לשמו
chatat shelo lishmo and the meat is still כשר. kosher. That's what
רב just said חטאת לשם חולין chatat leshem chulin is כשר. kosher.
But now he's going to qualify that. That's true when you know
it's a חטאת chatat and you're intending it to be treated as
חולין. chulin. But משום חולין mishum chulin if you assume that it's
חולין chulin you misunderstood what it was. Here you are in the
בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash and you figured somebody was just bringing you
their cow because they knew that there was a lot of שחיטה
going on or something. So you assumed it was חולין chulin okay
then פסולה psulah that is complete invalid if you misunderstood. Why? כי
דבעי מיניה שמואל מרב הונא Ki d'ba'ei minei Shmuel me-Rav Huna שמואל
Shmuel asked רב הונא Rav Huna מניין
למתעסק בקדשים שהוא פסול? Minayin le-misasek bekodshim she-hu pasul? How do you
know if somebody is like not even conscious of what they're doing
by קרבנות korbanot that it's invalid? Now what does מתעסק misasek mean?
מתעסק misasek could mean like I don't know I'm just like yawning
and I have a knife in my hand and accidentally I shecht
or I'm playing a knife game and I'm throwing knives at a
wall and it happens to shecht. That's one form of מתעסק. misasek.
תוספות Tosfos says that that מתעסק misasek is invalid even for חולין.
chulin. You have to by חולין chulin know that you're at least
cutting the throat of an animal. Okay but the מתעסק misasek here
could be a very narrow distinction. By חולין chulin you have to
know that you're cutting the throat of an animal but you don't
have to consciously be aware that it's making the meat כשר. kosher
That it's being done as a ritual act to slaughter you know
to כשר kosher. the meat. Maybe you're just doing it because you're
like some whatever person who gets pleasure from doing these things to
animals you know so some sadist or something like that. So okay
but so you don't have to consciously know that you're doing it
to make the meat כשר. kosher. By a קרבן korban you have
to know you're doing it to make the meat כשר. kosher, But
the other point is the מתעסק misasek being said here is you
also have to know that it's a קרבן. korban If you're so
oblivious that you think you're shechting in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
some normal cow and you're not aware that you're shechting a קרבן
korban okay then it's completely an irrelevant ritual act of שחיטה which
is very in... Interesting, right? It's sort of like it gets to
this whole question of לשמה. How much do you have to actively
do something to define it as a ritual act of שחיטת shechtas
קרבנות? korbonos? Or how much does the context define it by itself?
That's the question of סתם stam ולישמה. v'lishmo. So you might not
have to have in mind like that you are what do you
call it that you are excuse me you might not have to
mind what animal what type of קרבן it is, but if you're
so oblivious that you don't realize you're dealing with קרבנות, korbanos, then
the act is considered completely like not a שחיטה act of קרבנות.
korbanos. Okay. מנלן למתעסק בקדשים שפסול? Minalan l'misyasek b'kodashim she'pasul? שנאמר, Shene'emar,
ושחט את בן הבקר לפני ה'. v'shachat es ben habakar lifnei Hashem.
עד שתהא שחיטה לשם בן בקר. Ad she'tehei shechita l'shem ben bakar.
Now I don't understand the point of לשם בן בקר l'shem ben
bakar because that just means you have to know that it's a
cow. I would think that the more point would be לפני ה'.
lifnei Hashem. There has to be some awareness that it's in a
קרבן context. אמר ליה, Amar lei, זו בידינו היא. zu b'yadeinu hi.
We already knew that. לעכב מנלן? L'akev minalan? But how do you
know that בדיעבד b'di'eved it's no good? אמר ליה, Amar lei, לרצונכם
תזבחו. Lirtzonchem tizbachu. For your desire, meaning that it should be accepted.
לדעתכם תזבחו. L'da'atchem tizbachu. But also reading זביחו, z'vichu, meaning not just
that God should accept it, which is the word of, you know,
it's לרצון להם לפני ה', l'ratzon lahem lifnei Hashem, but it should
be your will, your רצון, ratzon, you should be consciously doing it.
Now again, consciously doing it as a קרבן seems to be the
extra point made here. So to repeat, the חידוש chiddush of רב
is that לשם חולין l'shem chullin is by a חטאת chatas for
the sake of something else is completely פסול. pasul. ולשם חולין, v'lshem
chullin, the meat is כשר, but it's not עולה לבעלים לשם חובה,
ola l'be'alim l'shem chova, which is an interesting middle state for חטאת
chatas we usually don't have. And then the final qualification is, that's
if you intentionally
misdirected it as a חולין. chullin. But if you actually were misunderstood
it to be a חולין chullin and you were oblivious, then that
would be considered מתעסק misyasek and that would be totally פסול. pasul.
Okay, and that would not only be true by a חטאת, chatas,
that would be true by an עולה or anything. That's not about
לשמה. That's about the issue of מתעסק. misyasek. Okay, we'll end here.